how would we really remit governance
itself this is really just how we even
govern ourselves in the 21st century and
how do we take advantage of the
technologies that are available now in
the knowledge base we have now to do
things very differently than we did in
the past how would you actually start
from scratch and really figure out a way
of governance in the broadest sense
which is collective problem solving yes
we do live in an environment right now
the technical and scientific frontier is
vastly further out than our actual
institutional capabilities take
advantage of and so we should be frankly
ashamed of ourselves if we were not
taking advantage of the current cutting
edge in faint places like evolutionary
biology cognitive neuroscience
complexity systems information
technology etc etc when we were building
something new because only idiots
wouldn't use the best tools that they
have so I love the step by step method
that Jordan laid out here which was to
first state your assumptions about what
the problems are to define a design
challenge as you see it to talk about
the resources that are available the
tools and technologies and other things
we have at our disposal and then to come
up with a prototype and I love the fact
that we're talking about physics and
complexity and neuroscience and
evolutionary biology and philosophy and
myths and metaphors maybe we'll get to
that a little bit as well but all of
that is critically important well one
thing that I like about it is that
framing democracy and police and making
a strong one solving it helps us
actually to find solutions and kind of
tackle problems as we tackle problems as
engineers and computer scientists and
looking for the best solutions clearly
most of the technologies now at least in
manufacturing production are moving
towards doing things at the local which
tends to point towards a social
governance occurring more at a community
level maybe at a city state level and
then interconnecting at a global level
using peer-to-peer and few too many
networks when I think of very
large-scale state transitions and a
complex network of networks operating at
lots of levels seems to me the
transition strategy has to be a fractal
one where things are created at the
local level which are self-consistent at
at intermediate love
and then at the national and the global
and if a system is well designed the
same principles ought to be applicable
at all those levels simultaneously I
think we have a little bit of a bias
here we we tend to think in terms of the
the old style of government the
industrial kind of ubiquitous mass
ideological forms of governance and men
were passed ideology ideology is dead
the only systems that seem to work or
you know and the p2p side are opt in
Nellie for instance a Singapore it said
okay we're going to expand our
city-state to 200 million of the best
people in the country or the world and
we're gonna adopt them as citizens and
we're going to stitch them together in a
variety of unique in interesting ways
well in that instance that you have a
city-state that virtual city-state that
could be extremely powerful and then do
much much more than what we see with the
current of physical governance
structures but we can't make the
assumption that's an opt-in decision by
a few self chosen experts in a
particular domain has any legitimacy for
all the people who are not involved so
this is why I think we we need to be
very careful it's possible to stay here
but you could imagine that kind of an
emergent situation here where where the
opt-in systems that would essentially be
aiming for this more superior way of
governance and that over time you know
it might compete or start to compete
with existing system and the ultimate
kind of clash or transition is something
we might be pointing to here patching
legacy systems is really not my thing
I'd rather challenge and put them out of
business so um I do think opt-in is is
it is the way it goes I am pretty
optimistic about our current forms of
governance and government with changes
in the current system we can actually
increase people's ability to self govern
themselves and that's that's already
happening so I'm not ready to throw the
current system to the garbage can
because I think it doesn't belong there
and also I'm very pragmatic so I want to
see change happening starting from now
so I think the key is the bridge we have
to find a way that representative
democracy can
look at civic practices and inspire
itself by these new civic practices
people should have a higher degree of
optimism than many people currently have
about our ability to actually not fall
into a collective failure of imagination
I want to help design a political system
for our Mars colony every time humans
have moved to a new place they've come
up with a new political system so the
exhaust even the idea of designing a
political system for a Mars colony or a
seasteading Institute or wherever we
want to go the idea and the license to
think about that will pay dividends here
on earth we actually of a vast territory
of exceptional ideas both the terms of
vision on how this thing plays out and
in terms of tools but how we effectively
deliberately move our way from where we
are to where we need to get it really is
almost an organizational challenge more
than anything else I suspect it may
actually be self producing the in the
process of figuring out how to solve the
problem of thinking about it we will
also be building the solution itself